A Finding Aid to the Joseph J. Greenberg Papers, 1939-1989, in the Archives of American Art.
Archives of American Art
Joseph J. Greenberg papers
1939-1989
Archives of American Art
Greenberg, Joseph J., 1915-1991
AAA.greejose
Archival Resource Key
0.5 Linear feet
The papers of Joseph J. Greenberg measure 0.5 linear feet and date from 1939-1989. The papers document Greenberg's career through biographical materials, including resumes and award certificates, professional correspondence, and printed material such as news clipping and exhibition catalogs. Also found is a scrapbook which contains clippings and catalogs, press releases, correspondence regarding his sculptures, a poem Greenberg wrote and notes. Photographic material contains photographs of Greenberg, his colleagues, and his artwork.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Joseph J. Greenberg measure 0.5 linear feet and date from 1939-1989. The papers document Greenberg's career through biographical materials, including resumes and award certificates, professional correspondence, and printed material such as news clipping and exhibition catalogs. Also found is a scrapbook which contains clippings and catalogs, press releases, correspondence regarding his sculptures, a poem Greenberg wrote and notes. Photographic material contains photographs of Greenberg, his colleagues, and his artwork.
Existence and Location of Copies
Material lent for microfilming is available on 35mm microfilm reel 4566 at Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan.
Separated Materials
The Archives of American Art also holds microfilm of material lent for microfilming (reel 4566) including two photograph albums containing photographs of Greenberg's sculptures. Loaned materials were returned to the lender, Mrs. Sheila Greenberg, and are not described in the collection container inventory.
Biographical / Historical
Joseph J. Greenberg (1915-1991) was a sculptor and educator from Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. Greenberg first became interested in sculpture as a child while attending the Oak Lane Country Day School and meeting sculptor Boris Blai, who was working as the school's art teacher. Years later Greenberg discovered Blai had become the director of the Tyler School of Art at Temple University prompting him to transfer there from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, where he had been studying engineering. Greenberg graduated from the Tyler School of Art in 1939 as a member of the first class of Tyler's complete five-year program. He went on to study in Italy where he had his first solo show in Rome and exhibited in the twenty sixth Venice Biennale. In 1951, Greenberg was the winner of a prize from the Metropolitan Museum of Art's National Sculpture Exhibition. He returned to Philadelphia in 1953 and continued living and working in the city until his death in 1991.
Greenberg was known for his large public sculptures in Pennsylvania include Bear and Cub in the Philadelphia Zoo, the aluminum seal of Pennsylvania on the State Office Building, and Symbol of Progress located in the heart of Bethlehem, PA by the entrance of the Bethlehem Area Public Library. In addition to his studio work, Greenberg taught at the Oak Lane Country Day School, the Tyler School, the New Hope Fine Arts Workshop, the Philadelphia Museum of Art and the Fleisher Memorial.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated 1991 by Sheila Greenberg, Joseph's widow, except for the photograph albums which were lent for microfilming. Collected and microfilmed as part of AAA's Philadelphia Arts Documentation Project.
Arrangement
Due to the small size of this collection the papers are arranged as one series.
Sculptors -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia; Educators -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia; Scrapbooks
- Joseph J. Greenberg Papers, 1939-1989; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1, OV 2
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical material includes resumes and award certificates for club memberships and fellowships. Correspondence is professional in nature and are from institutions such the Philadelphia Art Alliance, National Institute of Arts and Letters, The Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, The American Jewish Tercentenary, and others. Printed materials consist of clippings, exhibition catalogs and brochures featuring Greenberg's sculptures. Also found is a scrapbook which contains clippings and catalogs, press releases, correspondence regarding his sculptures, a poem Greenberg wrote and notes. Photographic material contains photographs of Greenberg, his colleagues and his artwork. Of note is a group photograph of artists on the main staircase of the Philadelphia Museum of Art.
  - Biographical Material, circa 1956-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1952-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Printed Material, Exhibition Announcements, 1952-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Printed Material, Brochures and Programs, 1955-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Printed Material, Exhibition Catalogs, 1940-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Printed Material, Exhibition Catalogs, 1962-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Printed Material, Exhibition Catalogs, 1972-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Printed Material, Clippings, 1939; 1952-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Scrapbook, 1941-1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Photographs, Greenberg and Colleagues, circa 1954-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Photographs, Artists at The Philadelphia Museum of Art, circa 1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Photographs, Works of Art, circa 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Photographs, Works of Art, circa 1956-1967; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 2)